It's always funny comparing the claims
across social media to the actual
scientific evidence. In fact, even
content that cites studies on vitamin K
gets a lot wrong. The reason I say that
is because I analyzed over 20 studies
being hyperfocused on several key
outcomes that are often discussed. So,
reversing arterial plaque, reversing
arterial calcification, and most
important, reducing cardiovascular
disease as a whole. Now, I think you'll
find that the results are sobering,
enlightening, and not necessarily
discouraging against vitamin K. We just
have to be a lot more nuanced in our
take as we often do. So, I watched and
read a lot of content on social media,
and often it refers to the studies that
show positive effects of vitamin K
supplementation, which might make you,
the consumer, think that vitamin K is a
LeBron James slam dunk for purchase. But
I'll start here. This is a systematic
review, meaning that the researchers
used a predefined criteria for putting
together a number of studies, so nine in
this case, to come to an overall
conclusion on vitamin K and
cardiovascular measures like arterial
plaque and arterial calcification.
Considering how positively people talk
about vitamin K, well, you'd you'd
clearly expect that this systematic
review would agree. But here is the
conclusion from this review. There's
presently a lack of randomized trial
evidence to support a beneficial role of
vitamin K in preventing the worsening of
surrogate measures of cardiovascular
disease. In short, vitamin K doesn't
have much evidence in its favor. As
horrifying or anger-causing as that
might be for vitamin K evangelists, the
reality is far more nuanced and may
still provide an avenue by which vitamin
K can be beneficial. This systematic
review did look at the plaque reversing
effects of vitamin K, for example. And
as you heard, the researchers were
unimpressed. But I decided to open and
analyze all of the included studies,
plus any additional ones that I could
find. And I discovered something
telling. First, these randomized control
trials showed without a doubt no effect
of vitamin K on arterial plaque.
Meanwhile, these two do indicate a
benefit. There are a number of
possibilities for that difference from
the amount of vitamin K consumed to the
type of vitamin K consumed or the length
of the studies. But there's actually a
theme here that carries through to the
data on arterial calcification too. So
let me touch on that before we return.
Unlike reversing arterial plaque, which
speaks to the dangerous soft plaque that
builds up in our arteries, calcified
plaque is well, plaque with calcium
deposits, and it's over the soft plaque.
There's a lot to say on that front that
I've covered in the past, and I won't
regurgitate it here, but the short of it
is that it's a different measure of the
plaque in your arteries. The ideal
scenario is having neither a clean pipe
through and through. So when we look at
the calcified plaque studies again
typically randomized control studies
here and we separate them by effect of
vitamin K on calcified plaque we see
these results. Not the most encouraging
result is it? We're again talking about
a minority of studies indicating an
effect and the majority by necessity
indicating no effect. That part is a bit
puzzling because one of the mechanisms
of action of vitamin K is to work
through an enzyme called MGK MGP excuse
me or matrix glin which is an enzyme
that is vitamin K dependent and it's
highly expressed in the arteries
undergoing calcification. Now typically
more MGP activity leads to inhibition of
the calcium deposits being deposited
thereby slowing the calcification
process. Now it does that by inhibiting
pro-alcification signaling within the
cells as well as binding directly to the
calcium crystals called hydroxy appatite
that are deposited in the plaque. Now
I'm telling you all that because MGP is
more active when it is caroxilated which
is just means that it's modified in such
a way that it makes it more active in
preventing calcification. So vitamin K
is critical to that process and reliably
across many studies and shown here there
is a reduction in uncarboxillated
or inactive MGP when vitamin K is
supplemented. The gray boxes are the
vitamin K group and the black is the
placebo group condition. Now, the lower
the boxes go over time, the less
inactive MGP is present. Measures
indicating activated MGP also confirm
these results. So, if we were to base
conclusions on this mechanism, we'd come
away thinking that vitamin K
supplementation does reduce arterial
calcification. Yet, as we saw from the
actual measures of calcification,
there's a greater amount of evidence
pointing toward that not being the case.
Okay. So, what do the soft plaque
studies and the calcified plaque studies
have in common that could shed some
light as to why studies disagree? And is
there hope for vitamin K? The answer to
the second question is yes. And the
answer to the first question is multiple
factors. One, the studies that typically
don't show an effect of vitamin K
supplementation use lower doses like
this one that was using less than 200
micrograms. And different types of
vitamin K like this one using vitamin K1
or infrequent consumption like this one
instructing to consume vitamin K only
three times per week. But that's not as
strong of a through line as looking at
studies that do show effectiveness,
which presents in people who are sicker
than average, as in people with
metabolic syndrome like diabetes. Most
studies indicating benefit were in
people with established heart disease,
kidney disease, or metabolic dysfunction
of some sort. So, could that be the
defining reason why some studies show no
benefit and others do indicate a
benefit? Well, it's certainly a
possibility, and I'd like to revisit
that point in a bit. For now, we'll just
summarize everything that we just went
over by saying that there's a ton of
mixed evidence. Some indicating vitamin
K improves arterial plaque, calcified or
not, and many studies indicate no
effect. I realize this doesn't offer
many answers, but I want you to sit back
and relax because as much as we often
worry about the plaque reversal and
calcification, the more important
question skips all of that and jumps
straight to does vitamin K protect
against cardiovascular disease as a
whole, regardless of the origin. In the
event that you want a deeper dive on all
of this, including the impact that
vitamin K has on arterioclerosis, the
stiffening of the arteries, or the
combination of vitamin K with vitamin D,
and if that might be more promising
avenue and more, then check out my full
analysis. It's included with a full
extended video, an article, a podcast, a
vetted supplement guide for all kinds of
conditions, and much more. It's all
included as a Physionic Insider. The
link to join the Physionic Insiders is
obviously as usual in the description. I
hope to see you there.
Okay, so to answer the overall question,
we typically can't rely on short-term
studies like what we've been focused on.
Though to give credit, some of the
randomized trials last several years,
which is very long. We should focus on
studies lasting many years, if not
decades. For example, over 21 years.
When we compare those who consume more
vitamin K1 or vitamin K2, we can see a
notable reduced risk of hospitalization
due to cardiovascular disease with
either. The blue is vitamin K1 and the
red is vitamin K2. If the lines drop
below 1.0, that dashed line there,
there's a reduced risk. So clearly both
indicate reduced risk. This remained
even when adjusting for all of these
potential factors.
Okay, these kinds of associations are
further confirmed across many studies
including another systematic review and
meta analysis of 21 studies and we even
see the relationship remain for vitamin
K1 and vitamin K2 with a bit stronger
evidence favoring vitamin K2. However,
the best available evidence in those
long-term studies tend to come from
studies that measure people's nutrient
intake many times over the course of the
study. And these studies tend to show
mixed results. For example, within the
same study, the researchers confirmed
this reduced risk of cardiovascular
disease with greater vitamin K intake
shown here. If you follow the blue line,
remember below 1.0 dotted line indicates
reduced heart disease risk. However,
that is only partially accounting for
other factors. And when we account for
more factors, the relationship weakens,
seen as the red line moves upwards. Then
the researchers factored in more aspects
of diet like fruit intake, fish intake
and the like and the relationship was
completely lost. Still this was not the
case when instead of looking at total
vitamin K consumption they looked at
consuming vitamin K rich vegetables. In
that instance even after all of the same
adjustments the heart-healthy
relationship remained. The point here
being that when we look at studies that
have weaker methodology and don't
account for nutrition as well, there's
an identified beneficial relationship
between vitamin K1 and cardiovascular
disease. However, when we look at
studies that account more rigorous
rigorously for nutrition and have more
rigorous methodology in general, we no
longer see that effect unless we look at
vitamin K1 consumption as a package deal
with vegetable high in vitamin K1. This
tells us that vitamin K1 is not
necessarily playing a direct role, but
is a marker of overall more well-rounded
nutrition. Still, these studies are
exclusively looking at vitamin K1, not
vitamin K2. And there's other studies
that do look at vitamin K2, but since
vitamin K2 comes from dairy and meats,
they did not adjust for fruit and
vegetable intake, which they did for
vitamin K1. They adjusted for calcium
intake and generally showed that vitamin
K2 still tracked with reduced heart
disease risk. So this may strengthen the
idea that we should lean toward vitamin
K2 over vitamin K1. That interpretation
is on wobbly foundation though because
the methodology of these studies is not
as strong as the vitamin K1 studies that
we just went over. Honestly, when trying
to pack the nuances of 20 plus studies
into a single analysis and still keeping
it brief, I get this sense that the
analysis is like expanding against
multiple taught chains being held down
by 100 burly strong men and oxen. She's
going to blow. Hold steady, men.
because there's so much more to say. But
I really think that if I continued, I'd
be diving us deeper into confusion
before emerging on the other end with
some clarity. So why don't we just skip
over the treacherously deep puddle and
land safely on the other side of
clarity? Now, here's where I land on all
this. If you were convinced that vitamin
K had rock solid evidence behind it, I'd
go back to your source and check how
many studies that source looked at
because out of 10 or so randomized
control trials, the majority indicate
vitamin K is ineffective against
arterial plaque and arterial
calcification. I think that alone is a
bombshell. We could argue that it might
be beneficial for people who are
metabolically compromised like with
diabetes, cardiovascular disease and so
on. But the data is so mixed including
in those individuals that I don't feel
confident in that throughine based on
randomized control trials. So when we
broaden to overall cardiovascular
disease, we're now bringing in huge
studies looking at associations albeit
heavily adjusted between vitamin K and
heart disease.
And the best evidence on vitamin K1
indicates the relationship just isn't
there except for the context of eating
vitamin vitamin K1 rich foods which
contribute to protecting against
cardiovascular disease. On the other
hand, vitamin K2 has a signal for
benefit. The evidence quality isn't
quite as good, but there's multiple
lines that indicate that that a vitamin
K2 intake is increased, there's reduced
risk of heart disease. That same
evidence points to vitamin K2 having an
independent effect. The bottom line is
that there's some big holes in the data
that we need to fill, but the current
evidence leans in favor of vitamin K2
being a benefit against cardiovascular
disease. Though I don't think we can
claim that with any strong certainty,
much like the original systematic review
that we discussed that vitamin K
promotes arterial plaque removal or
slowing. Assuming that you're bullish on
vitamin K supplementation specifically,
the doses most often used to effect were
around 200 to 400 micrograms
per day of vitamin K2. But also keep in
mind the risk benefit of of it all. For
example, in the systematic review that
the researchers point out that vitamin K
is usually pretty well tolerated, except
there are some studies that indicated
bad reactions, including bleeding events
in people taking anti-coagulant
medications as well, which makes sense
considering that vitamin K is heavily
involved in the clotting cascade. So, it
might be okay for anyone not on certain
medications, but that's a factor that
you'll want to throw into the equation
even more here. So, as always, but
especially now, check in with your
physician. But just because vitamin K
isn't as impressive, or at least the
evidence isn't, doesn't mean that there
aren't other ways of improving your
cardiovascular health. What's this?
Another video, you say? Click right
here.
I knew this was a lot. Thanks for
sticking out with me. I appreciate it.
I'll be back to take you down another
rabbit hole soon.